Heloise Durant Rose Letters
Heloise Durant Rose Letters
1873-1945
Rose, Heloise Durant.
121 items (SC).
Papers of the American author, lecturer, founder of the Dante League of America. Incoming personal and business correspondence, much of it in connection with the Dante League in particular and the promotion of the arts in general.
Correspondents include Maude Adams, Samuel W. Baker, Bruce Barton, Poultney Bigelow, Arthur Brisbane, Andrew Carnegie, William B. Carpenter, Paul Claudel, Frank Crane, Chauncey Depew, John A. Dix, Morgan Dix, Lucie Duff Gordon, Norman Bel Geddes, Virginia Gildersleeve, Abram S. Hewitt, John Haynes Holmes, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Charles Evans Hughes, Joyce Kilmer, F.F. Mackay, Edwin Markham, Adolph S. Ochs, George F. Peabody, Henry C. Potter, George Haven Putnam, Whitelaw Reid, James Whitcomb Riley, Anne Thackeray Ritchie, Corinne Roosevelt Robinson, Theodore Roosevelt, Luigi Rossi, Elizabeth Sewell, Otis Skinner, Helen Taft, Marie Taglioni, William Roscoe Thayer, Spencer Trask, Charles Dudley Warner, Helen Westley, Post Wheeler, Andrew D. White, Woodrow Wilson, and others.
149263
Biographical History
Heloise Durant Rose (1854?-1943) was an American author, playwright, and critic. The daughter of Heloise Durant and Union Pacific Railroad industrialist Thomas Clark Durant, she attended private schools in Europe and America and was fluent in Italian, French, German and Arabic.
Rose was a book reviewer for the New York Times and the author of plays, poems, essays, articles and short stories. Her dramatic poem Dante (1910) was translated into Italian and is believed to be the first American play produced on the Italian stage.
Rose founded the Dante League in 1917 "for popular propaganda for the study of Dante" and was a signatory of the "Memorial to the Columbia College Board of Trustees," an 1883 petition to allow female students to attend lectures and examinations at Columbia College. (Other signers included Parke Godwin, Georgina Schuyler, Caroline Sterling Choate, Susan B. Anthony, Chauncey M. Depew, Emma Lazarus, Josephine Shaw Lowell, Theodore Roosevelt, Charles Comfort Tiffany.)
[Portions of this biographical sketch adapted from the article "Rose, Heloise Durant" in the 1935 edition of Who's Who and What to See in Florida: A Standard Biographical Reference Book of Florida, pp 225-226.]
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Heloise Durant Rose Letters consist of incoming personal and business correspondence, much of which is in connection with the Dante League of America, of which Mrs. Rose was the founder. Correspondents include authors (Poultney Bigelow, Oliver Wendell Holmes, Joyce Kilmer, Edwin Markham, James Whitcomb Riley, Corinne Roosevelt Robinson, William Roscoe Thayer, Post Wheeler); publishers (Arthur Brisbane, G. H. Putnam); diplomats (Paul Claudel, Whitelaw Reid); and educators (Virginia Gildersleeve, Andrew D. White).
Regarding the production of her dramatic poem, Dante, Mrs. Rose received correspondence from several theatrical people including Maude Adams, Normal Bel Geddes, Adeline Genee, F. F. McKay, Otis Skinner, and Helen Westley. The play was said to be the first American drama produced for the Italian stage.
In the promotion of the arts and an appreciation of Dante in the United States, Rose cultivated the support of political figures (Chauncey M. Depew, John A. Dix, Abram S. Hewitt, Charles Evans Hughes, Theodore Roosevelt, Woodrow Wilson) and philanthropists (Andrew Carnegie, George Foster Peabody, Spencer Trask).
Among the personal correspondence are letters of condolence on the death of Rose's first husband, Arthur Frethey, and items from several clergymen, including James Darlington, Morgan Dix, John Haynes Holmes, William Thomas Manning, and Henry Potter. Also present are two personal letters from Anne Thackeray Ritchie, daughter of novelist William Makepeace Thackeray.
Arrangement of the Collection
Letters are arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
Subject and Genre Headings
Women Authors; Adams, Maude, 1872-1953.; Baker, Samuel White, Sir, 1821-1893.; Barton, Bruce, 1886-1967.; Bigelow, Poultney, 1855-1954.; Brisbane, Arthur, 1864-1936.; Carnegie, Andrew, 1835-1919.; Carpenter, William Boyd, 1841-1918.; Claudel, Paul, 1868-1955.; Crane, Frank, 1873-1948.; Dante Alighieri, 1265-1321 -- Societies, periodicals, etc.; Depew, Chauncey M. (Chauncey Mitchell), 1834-1928.; Dix, John A. (John Adams), 1798-1879.; Dix, Morgan, 1827-1908.; Duff Gordon, Lucie, Lady, 1821-1869.; Geddes, Norman Bel, 1893-1958.; Gildersleeve, Virginia Crocheron, 1877-1965.; Hewitt, Abram S. (Abram Stevens), 1822-1903.; Holmes, John Haynes, 1879-1964.; Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1809-1894.; Hughes, Charles Evans, 1862-1948.; Kilmer, Joyce, 1886-1918.; Mackay, F. F. (Frank Findley), 1832-1923.; Markham, Edwin, 1852-1940.; Ochs, Adolph S. (Adolph Simon), 1858-1935.; Peabody, George Foster, 1852-1938.; Potter, Henry Codman, 1834-1908.; Putnam, George Haven, 1844-1930.; Reid, Whitelaw, 1837-1912.; Riley, James Whitcomb, 1849-1916.; Ritchie, Anne Thackeray, 1837-1919.; Robinson, Corinne Roosevelt, 1861-1933.; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919.; Rose, Heloise Durant.; Rossi, Luigi Melano.; Sewell, Elizabeth Missing, 1815-1906.; Skinner, Otis, 1858-1942.; Taft, Helen Herron, 1861-1943.; Taglioni, Marie, 1804-1884.; Thayer, William Roscoe, 1859-1923.; Trask, Spencer, 1844-1909.; Warner, Charles Dudley, 1829-1900.; Westley, Helen, 1875 or 1879-1942.; Wheeler, Post, 1869-1956.; White, Andrew Dickson, 1832-1918.; Wilson, Woodrow, 1856-1924.; Dante League of America.; Upper class -- United States.; United States -- Intellectual life.; United States -- Social life and customs.; Correspondence.; Authors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Adams, Maude, 10 Dec 1897; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Baker, Samuel White, 9 Sep 1891; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Barton, Bruce, 9 Jul 1918; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Bigelow, Poultney, 1906-1945; 20 items (Sc 31)
  - Brisbane, Arthur, 1920; 1932; 4 items (Sc 31)
  - Carnegie, Andrew, 1884-1909; 5 items (Sc 31)
  - Carpenter, William Boyd, 29 May 1912; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Claudel, Paul, 9 Feb 1911; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Cooper, Julia, undated; 2 items (Sc 31)
  - Crane, Frank, 24 Nov 1916; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Darlington, James Henry, 1928; 2 items (Sc 31)
  - Depew, Chauncey M., 1917-1926; 5 items (Sc 31)
  - Dix, John A., 1873; 1878; 2 items (Sc 31)
  - Dix, Morgan, 5 Oct 1882; undated; 3 items (Sc 31)
  - Duff Gordon, Lucie, Lady, undated; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Geddes, Norman Bel, 2 Apr 1928; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Genee, Adeline, 16 Jan 1910; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Gildersleeve, Virginia Crocheron, 25 Jan 1917; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Hewitt, Abram Stevens, 29 Nov 1898; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Hewitt, Sarah Amelia, 14 Jul 1894; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Holmes, John Haynes, 29 Jan 1915; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Holmes, Oliver Wendell, 1886; 1894; 2 items (Sc 31)
  - Hughes, Charles Evans, 1920-1927; 4 items (Sc 31)
  - Kilmer, Joyce, 5 Feb 1916; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Mackay, Frank Findlay, 16 Jul 1903; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Manning, William Thomas, 1906; 1910,; 1921; 3 items (Sc 31)
  - Markham, Edwin, 17 Jun 1916; undated; 2 items (Sc 31)
  - Ochs, Adolph S., 6 Sep 1921; undated; 2 items (Sc 31)
  - Peabody, George Foster, 18 Nov 1902; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Potter, Henry Codman, 1902; 1903,; 1907; 4 items (Sc 31)
  - Power, Tyrone, undated; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Pulitzer, Walter, 1923; undated; 2 items (Sc 31)
  - Putnam, George Haven, 19 Apr 1913; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Reid, Whitelaw, 16 Nov 1896; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Riley, James Whitcomb, 19 Nov 1915; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Ritchie, Anne Thackeray, 16 Nov 1897; undated; 2 items (Sc 31)
  - Robinson, Corinne Roosevelt, undated; 2 items (Sc 31)
  - Roosevelt, Theodore, 23 Dec 1890; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Rossi, Luigi Melano, 17 Nov 1923; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Sartain, William, 1 Jul 1924; undated; 2 items (Sc 31)
  - Sewell, Elizabeth Missing, undated; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Skinner, Maud Durbin, 17 Feb 1922; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Taft, Helen Herron, 8 Feb 1911; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Taglioni, Marie, 1880; 1883,; undated; 3 items (Sc 31)
  - Thayer, William Roscoe, 1917; 1920,; 1921; 3 items (Sc 31)
  - Trask, Spencer, 8 May 1902; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Warner, Charles Dudley, 20 Nov 1893; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Westley, Helen, 6 Jun 1940; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Wheeler, Post, 1901; 1902,; undated; 3 items (Sc 31)
  - Wilson, Woodrow, 5 Jan 1914; 1 items (Sc 31)
  - Miscellaneous, 1899; 1909,; undated; items (Sc 31)